Finding Aid for Otto Webster Haisley Papers, 1917-1959
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Otto Webster Haisley Papers 1917-1959, 1940-1953
Haisley, Otto Webster, 1884-1959.
2.3 linear feet
88378 Aa 2
Ann Arbor, Michigan educator and superintendent of schools; personal and professional papers relating to his work as school superintendent; also publications, speeches, correspondence, family materials, and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Alice Haisley, wife of Otto W. Haisley (donor no. 6581 ) and came to the library in 1988.
The collection is open to research.
Otto W. Haisley (1884-1959) was born in Fairmount, Indiana. He attended Earlham College at Richmond, Indiana, the University of Michigan, the University of Wisconsin, and Columbia University. From 1913 to 1916 he taught high school in San Antonio, Texas, after which he began a long career as a school superintendent, first in Niles, Michigan (1917-1924), then in Ann Arbor, Michigan (1924-1953). In his role as superintendent, Haisley worked toward rounding out the strict academic curriculum with vocational courses. His goal was to expand the number and range of non-academic courses in order to benefit those students not intending to go to college.
One of Haisley's major contributions to his profession was his formula for establishing salaries for superintendents, which was used nationwide. Haisley was active in many associations and clubs, including the Michigan Association of School Administrators, National Educational Association, Elks Club, and Rotary Club.
The Otto W. Haisley collection consists of five series: Personal (1934-1960); Correspondence (1906-1958); Publications, Speeches, and Clippings (1924-1954); Superintendent's Office (1929-1954); Family Papers; and Photographs. Within each series, files are arranged alphabetically by topic.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor Public Schools.; Education--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Schools--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Soviet Union.; Public schools--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.). Board of Education.; Haisley, Otto Webster, 1884-1959.; Haisley family.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Personal
  The Personal series (0.2 linear ft.) contains material associated with Haisley's life outside the education profession. Included are observances from his trip to Russia (1934), his original poetry, and plans for building a cottage at Topinabee, Michigan. The "Personal" file contains several of Haisley's reminiscences about his family and about growing up in Indiana.
  - Awards (Box 1)
  - Cottage Plans (Topinabee, MI) 1941 (Box 1)
  - Inter-City Investment Club of Ann Arbor 1960 (Box 1)
  - Obituaries (Otto Haisley) 1959 (Box 1)
  - Personal (Box 1)
  - Poetry and Artwork (Box 1)
  - Rotary Club (Box 1)
  - Trip to Russia 1934, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series (0.3 linear ft.) contains letters dealing with a wide variety of subjects, both personal and professional in nature. There is evidence of Haisley's communication with other school officials in Michigan and in other states regarding educational and curriculum issues, as well as other professional concerns. Also included are letters which describe Haisley's personal activities, such as his involvement in Rotary and his personal support of his colleagues.
  - 1906-1957, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Paul Remus 1927-1941 (Box 1)
  - Recommendations 1928-1939 (Box 1)
  - Retirement 1952 (Box 1)
  - Retirement Testimonial Letters 1953 (Box 1)
  - Tenure Proposal 1938-1941 (Box 1)
- Publications, Speeches and Clippings
  Publications, Speeches, and Clippings (0.5 linear ft.) contains Haisley's speeches and publications as well as a folder and an unbound scrapbook of newspaper clippings. The topics covered in the speeches range from teacher training to school construction. This range of interest is also apparent in Haisley's articles, which deal not only with the role of the superintendent, and the determination of his salary, but also with numerous other aspects of school administration. Most of the clippings document Haisley's well-publicized conflict with the Board of Education over his dismissal in May 1941. Following often bitter discussions of his educational methods and policies in a subsequent school board election, Haisley was reappointed in September 1941.
  - Publications 1927-1951, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Speeches undated (Box 1)
  - Speeches 1924-1944 (Box 1)
  - Speeches 1947-1954 (Box 1)
  - Speech and Article Material (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings 1932-1953 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook (unbound) (Box 1)
- Superintendent's Office
  The Superintendent's Office, (.8 linear foot) series contains material from professional organizations with which Haisley was associated or an active participant. Included here are documents that reflect the activities and concerns of a school superintendent. Also included here are more materials documenting Haisley's dismissal and reappointment by the Board of Education in 1941.
  - Architects-Reports on 1950 (Box 2)
  - Board of Education, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Certification of Superintendent's Committee 1939 (Box 2)
  - Committee Work 1948-1950 (Box 2)
  - Community School Service Program 1951 (Box 2)
  - Council of Social Agencies (Box 2)
  - Employment of Youth 1950 (Box 2)
  - Financing Ann Arbor School Building Program 1949 (Box 2)
  - Fixing the salary of the Superintendent of Schools 1949 (Box 2)
  - Graduation Programs 1929-1953 (Box 2)
  - Haisley Contract Renewal 1941 (Box 2)
  - Haisley vs. the Board of Education 1941 (Box 2)
  - Industrial Arts Committee 1946 (Box 2)
  - Library 1924 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Association of School Administrators 1949-1953, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Michigan Commission on Education Policies, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Michigan Education Association 1932 (Box 2)
  - Midwest Administration Center 1951-1954 (Box 2)
  - National Citizens' Commission for the Public Schools 1950 (Box 2)
  - School Board Survey. 1941 (Box 2)
  - School Bulletins 1950 (Box 2)
  - School Evaluations 1950 (Box 2)
  - Teacher Retirement Allowances 1941-1953 (Box 2)
  - Teacher Salary 1933-1936 (Box 2)
  - Youth and the Future of America 1950 (Box 2)
- Family Papers
  The Family Papers series (0.2 linear feet) is comprised largely of records dealing with the history of the families of Otto and Alice Haisley. There is substantial information documenting the history of Alice Haisley's family, on her father's side (Callender and Winslow) and on her mother's side (Sowers). Undated notes trace the Callender family back to the 18th century, and other materials trace the origins of the names. Similarly detailed evidence is available for the Haisley family and its precursors (e.g. Hiatt and Rush). Virtually all the "Callender Family Correspondence" deals with the history of the Callender and Winslow families, whereas the "Haisley Family Correspondence," consists of letters Otto wrote to his mother while he was teaching in San Antonio. Also included in this series are obituaries following Haisley's death in 1959.
  - Callender Family History 1904-1952, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Correspondence
    - Callender Family 1893-1948 (Box 2)
    - Haisley Family 1913-1916 (Box 2)
  - Haisley Family History (Box 2)
  - Sowers Family History (Box 2)
    (Alice Haisley's maternal grandmother)
  - Winslow Family History (Box 2)
    (Alice Haisley's paternal grandmother)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series (0.3 linear feet) includes numerous portraits of Otto Haisley, taken at various ages. Very completely represented are Haisley's immediate family: his wife and his two daughters, Sylvia and Virginia. Also present are images of Alice Haisley's family, including formal, professional portraits of her father, Sherman D. Callender, a Detroit judge. There are also images of the Ann Arbor Board of Education (1950-1952), the Ann Arbor Community Council (1949-1950), the American Association of School Administrators State Presidents' Meeting (Chicago, 1951), and the Michigan Council on Educational Policies (1950).
  - Ann Arbor Teachers Club Album May 1949 (Box 3)
  - Callender Family, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Haisley Family, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Otto Haisley-Portraits (Box 3)
  - Otto Haisley and friends [high school?] (Box 3)
  - Winslow Family grave markers (Box 3)
  - Personal/Family (Box 3)
  - Professional, 3 folders (Box 3)